Civil Rights History Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: Interviews
  - Gwendolyn Annette Duncan oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Saint Augustine, Florida, September 14, 2011
    Summary: Gwendolyn Duncan recalls her family history in Saint Augustine, Florida, watching a Ku Klux Klan parade through the black neighborhood of Lincolnville, and integrating a white school. She discusses the efforts in St. Augustine to commemorate the local Civil Rights Movement, including the ACCORD Freedom Trail.
    - Moving Images, 2 video files of 2 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (34 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0047_mv01-02
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (18 pages); afc2010039_crhp0047_duncan_transcript (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Robert Bagner Hayling oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Saint Augustine, Florida, September 14, 2011
    Biographical History: Robert Hayling was born in 1929 in Tallahassee, Florida, married Athea Hayling, and had three children. He attended Florida A&M College and Meharry Medical College and worked as a dentist. He was the principal leader of the Saint Augustine movement in the early 1960s.
    Summary: Robert Hayling recalls serving in the air force during World War II, attending the Meharry Dental School, and participating in civil rights protests in Nashville, Tennessee. He remembers starting his dental practice in St. Augustine, Florida, leading the local National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) youth group, and the exclusion of African Americans from St. Augustine's 400th anniversary celebration, and being attacked by the Ku Klux Klan. He also discusses resigning from the NAACP, the support of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) for local protests, and his move to Cocoa, Florida.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (115 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0048_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (45 pages); afc2010039_crhp0048_hayling_transcript (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Gwendolyn Zoharah Simmons oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Gainesville, Florida, September 14, 2011
    Biographical History: Gwendolyn Simmons was born in 1944 in Memphis, Tennessee, and had one daughter. She attended Spelman College, Antioch University, and Temple University. She worked as a professor of religion at the University of Florida. She was a civil rights activist and member of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC).
    Summary: Gwendolyn Simmons recalls joining the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) while a student at Spelman College. She remembers directing SNCC's voter registration and Freedom School, called the Freedom Summer Project in Laurel, Mississippi. She discusses learning about Black Nationalism in New York, the decision in SNCC to expel white members, and her work with the American Friends Service Committee's Program on Government Surveillance and Citizens' Rights to interview members of organizations investigated by the FBI's Counterintelligence Program (COINTELPRO).
    - Moving Images, 5 video files of 5 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (97 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0049_mv01-05
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (43 pages); afc2010039_crhp0049_simmons_transcript (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Shirley Miller Sherrod oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Albany, Georgia, September 15, 2011
    Biographical History: Shirley Sherrod was born in 1948 in Baker County, Georgia and married Charles Sherrod in 1966. She attended Fort Valley State College and Albany State University, worked as a community organizer in rural farming and land issues, and was head of Federation of Southern Cooperatives.
    Summary: Shirley Sherrod recalls growing up on a farm in Baker County, Georgia, her father's murder, and joining the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). She remembers traveling to Washington, D. C., to protest the Justice Department, and the attacks on her husband, Reverend Charles Sherrod, a civil rights leader in Albany, Georgia. She also discusses starting the New Communities Land Trust and working for the Federation of Southern Cooperatives and other organizations to help African American farmers.
    - Moving Images, 12 video files of 12 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (104 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0050_mv01-12
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (49 pages); afc2010039_crhp0050_sherrodshirley_transcript (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Kathleen Cleaver oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Atlanta, Georgia, September 16, 2011
    Biographical History: Kathleen Cleaver was born in 1945 in Dallas, Texas, married Eldridge Cleaver, and had two children. She attended Oberlin College, Barnard College, and Yale University, and worked as a political activist, attorney, and professor. She is noted for her involvement with the Black Panther Party with Eldridge Cleaver.
    Summary: Kathleen Cleaver recalls growing up in Tuskegee, Alabama, India and the Philippines while her father worked for the foreign service. She remembers dropping out of college to work for the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) as a secretary, and witnessing the dissolution of that organization. She discusses meeting her husband, Eldridge Cleaver, joining the Black Panther Party, and organizing against police brutality.
    - Moving Images, 10 video files of 10 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (123 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0051_mv01-10
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (57 pages); afc2010039_crhp0051_cleaver_transcript (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Candie Carawan and Guy Hughes Carawan oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in New Market, Tennessee, September 19, 2011
    Biographical History: Candie Carawan was born in 1939 in Los Angeles, California, married Guy Carawan in 1961 and had two children. She attended Pomona College and worked at the Highlander Folk Center as a cultural educator, singer, artist and potter.
    Biographical History: Guy Carawan was born in 1927 in Los Angeles, California, married Noel Oliver in 1954 (d. 1958) and Candie Anderson in 1961 and had two children. He attended Occidental College, UCLA, MA and worked at the Highlander Folk Center as music director, collector and performing musician.
    Summary: Candie Carawan recalls attending Fisk University as an exchange student and meeting civil rights activists in Nashville, Tennessee. She discusses meeting Guy Carawan at the Highlander Folk School, the importance of music to the civil rights movement, and Guy's work to record singers involved with the movement. The two perform several songs, including Tree of Life, Eyes on the Prize, and We Shall Overcome.
    - Moving Images, 5 video files of 5 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (54 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0052_mv01-05
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (29 pages); afc2010039_crhp0052_carawan_transcript (Box-folder 4/8)
  - David Mercer Ackerman and Satoko Ito Ackerman oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Washington, D.C., September 20, 2011
    Biographical History: David M. Ackerman was born in 1942 in Savanna, Illinois, married Satoko Ito in 1967 and had one child. He attended Knox College, the Chicago Theological Seminary and Georgetown Law Center, and worked as an attorney.
    Biographical History: Satoko Ito Ackerman was born December 16, 1939 in Osaka, Japan to Masaru and Hiroko Ito. Her siblings were Seiji and Yoshiko. She married David Ackerman in 1967 and had one child, Julienna. She attended Yankton College, BA and Chicago Theological, MA and worked in child care and public policy.
    Summary: David and Satoko Ackerman recall meeting at the Chicago Theological Seminary and remember their classmate Jesse Jackson urging students to attend the Selma to Montgomery March. They recall traveling to Selma, participating in the march, and their later life in Silver Spring, Maryland.
    - Moving Images, 6 video files of 6 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (62 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0053_mv01-06
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (30 pages); afc2010039_crhp0053_ackermans_transcript (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Dorie Ann Ladner and Joyce Ladner oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Washington, D.C., September 20, 2011
    Biographical History: Dorie Ladner was born in 1942 in Hattiesburg, Mississippi. She attended Jackson State College, Tougaloo College and Howard University and worked as a social worker.
    Biographical History: Joyce Ladner was born in 1943 in Battles, Mississippi, married Walter Carrington and attended Jackson State College; Tougaloo College, BA; Washington University-St. Louis, MA, PhD; and worked as a professor.
    Summary: Doris and Joyce Ladner discuss organizing for the March on Washington with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). Dorie Ladner recalls her work with SNCC in Natchez, Mississippi, and the murder and trial of Medgar Evers. They both remember growing up in Palmers Crossing, Mississippi, their family history, joining the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) youth chapter led by Clyde Kennard, and the impact that Emmett Till's murder had on their generation. Doris also recalls attending Tougaloo College, staying at the Freedom House in Jackson, Mississippi, and organizing the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party.
    - Moving Images, 7 video files of 7 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (121 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0054_mv01-07
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (73 pages); afc2010039_crhp0054_ladners_transcript (Box-folder 4/10)
  - William Lamar Strickland oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Amherst, Massachusetts, September 23, 2011
    Biographical History: William Strickland was born in 1937 in Boston, Massachusetts. He attended Harvard University and worked as a professor of political science and Afro-American Studies at the University of Massachusetts Amherst.
    Summary: William Strickland recalls growing up in Boston, Massachusetts, attending Boston Latin High School and Harvard University, and serving as a Marine. He remembers his friendship with Malcolm X, joining the Northern Student Movement, and his work with Vincent Harding and the Institute of the Black World. He also discusses the current research on Malcolm X and his opinions on politics.
    - Moving Images, 12 video files of 12 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (130 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0055_mv01-12
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (56 pages); afc2010039_crhp0055_strickland_transcript (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Carrie Lamar Young oral history interview conducted by Joseph Mosnier in Little Rock, Arkansas, September 26, 2011
    Biographical History: Carrie Young was born in 1948 in Barton, Arkansas, married Howard L. Himmelbaum in 1967 and later Carl E. Young, and had one child. She attended the Opportunity Industrialization Center and the University of Arkansas-Little Rock, and worked as a keypunch operator, accounting clerk, publication printing, and in data entry and administrative work.
    Summary: Carrie Young recalls growing up in on a farm, moving to West Helena, Arkansas, with her family, and meeting civil rights organizers from the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), including Myrtle Glascoe, Bill Hansen, and Howard Himmelbaum. She remembers registering voters, gathering signatures to overturn a poll tax, and protesting at the Arkansas state capitol. She discusses her marriage to Howard Himmelbaum, suing her employer for discrimination, and working with the group Black United Youth in Little Rock, Arkansas.
    - Moving Images, 9 video files of 9 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (125 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0056_mv01-09
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (65 pages); afc2010039_crhp0056_young_transcript (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Elmer Dixon oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in Seattle, Washington, February 28, 2013
    Biographical History: Elmer Dixon was the co-chair of the Seattle, Washington, chapter of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and also established the Seattle chapter of the Black Panther Party with his brother, Aaron Dixon. He later worked in the field of diversity and cross-cultural communication.
    Summary: Elmer Dixon discusses his childhood in Chicago, Illinois and Seattle, Washington, where he marched with Martin Luther King, Jr., and heard Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) leader Stokely Carmichael speak. At 17 he met Black Panthers Bobby Seale and Huey Newton in Oakland and established, with his brother Aaron Dixon as Defense Captain, the Seattle chapter of the Black Panther Party. Dixon discusses his work with the Panthers, the survival of several of the programs he started, including a health clinic, his work after the Panther chapter closed down in 1978, and his current position as director of an executive consulting firm specializing in diversity issues.
    - Moving Images, 11 video files of 11 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (152 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0057_mv01-11
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (66 pages); afc2010039_crhp0057_Dixon_transcript
  - Steven McNichols oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in Burlingame, California, March 1, 2013
    Biographical History: Steven McNichols was a freedom rider with the Congress of Racial Equality and civil rights director of the National Student Association. He attended the University of California, Los Angeles and the University of Texas at Austin. He was elected Civil Rights Director of the National Student Association, supported the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, and assisted the Delta Ministry and Department of Agriculture with distributing surplus food to poor African Americans in Mississippi. He later worked for Mayor Tom Bradley of Los Angeles and pursued a law degree and career as an employment discrimination attorney.
    Summary: Steven McNichols discussed his childhood in New York City, his mother's illnesses and attending the University of California, Los Angeles in 1958. He became involved in politics through the National Student Federation and National Student Association, and participated in the Freedom Rides, riding a train from Los Angeles, California, to Houston, Texas. He also discusses his work with the Delta Ministry, the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, and the 1964 Democratic Party convention.
    - Moving Images, 11 video files of 11 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (137 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0058_mv01-11
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (51 pages); afc2010039_crhp0058_McNichols_transcript
  - Mildred Pitts Walter oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in San Mateo, California, March 1, 2013
    Biographical History: Mildred Pitts Walter and her husband, Earl Walter, were active in the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) in the late 1950s helping to desegregate housing in California. She also helped recruit Freedom Riders from California. She later became a teacher and prolific children's book author.
    Summary: Mildred Pitts Walter discusses her early life in Louisiana, attending Southern University, and moving to Los Angeles in 1944. Pitts recalls meeting Earl Walter whom she married two years later, her work with Earl who headed the Los Angeles chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) from 1951 to 1963, CORE pickets of housing developers in Los Angeles, and her work as a clerk in the LA school district while getting her teaching credentials. She also discusses her career writing over 20 books for children, her work with a national association of nurses to develop culturally sensitive training, marching in the Soviet Union for peace, her ideas about civil rights and human rights.
    - Moving Images, 5 video files of 5 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (91 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0059_mv01-05
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (36 pages); afc2010039_crhp0059_Walter_transcript
  - Amos C. Brown oral history interview conducted by David P. Cline in San Francisco, California, March 2, 2013
    Biographical History: The Rev. Dr. Amos C. Brown was a civil rights activist in Jackson, Mississippi. He attended Morehouse College, Crozer Theological Seminary, and United Theological Seminary. He served as pastor of San Francisco's Third Baptist Church and was a board member of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
    Summary: Reverend Dr. Amos Brown discusses his childhood in Jackson, Mississippi and meeting Medgar Evers, who quickly became his mentor. Brown was a leader in the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) as a teenager, leading the Jackson chapter and then the whole state Youth Council and traveling with Mr. Evers across the country to attend a national conference. He was asked to leave his high school for making comments to the Cleveland Plain Dealer about unequal schools for blacks, and remembers his participation in a 1961 Freedom Ride, his travel to Africa as part of Operation Crossroads Africa, and his work at Third Baptist Church on various social causes.
    - Moving Images, 8 video files of 8 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (119 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0060_mv01-08
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (41 pages); afc2010039_crhp0060_Brown_transcript
  - Clifford Browner oral history interview conducted by Hasan Kwame Jeffries in Albany, Georgia, March 9, 2013
    Biographical History: Clifford Browner was a civil rights activist in Terrell County, Georgia. He attended Albany State University and joined the Army, and eventually worked in factories in Flint, Michigan, and Atlanta, Georgia.
    Summary: Clifford Browner discusses his childhood in Sasser, Georgia, and how he came to be involved in the Southwest Georgia Movement for civil rights in the early 1960s. He describes mass meetings at Mount Olive Baptist Church, protesting racial segregation at his high school, and participating in the March on Washington. He concludes the interview by evaluating the changes he has seen in southwest Georgia over his lifetime.
    - Moving Images, 2 video files of 2 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (65 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0061_mv01-02
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (40 pages); afc2010039_crhp0061_Browner_transcript
  - Lucius Holloway, Sr., and Emma Kate Holloway oral history interview conducted by Hasan Kwame Jeffries in Albany, Georgia, March 9, 2013
    Biographical History: Lucius Holloway, Sr., was a civil rights activist in Terrell County, Georgia, Vice President of the local National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), and the plaintiff in a voter registration court case, Holloway v. Wise. He later became County Commissioner of Terrell County.
    Biographical History: Emma Kate Holloway was a civil rights activist in Terrell County, Georgia. She also worked as a beautician.
    Summary: In this short interview, Lucius Holloway, Sr., and Emma Kate Holloway describe their experiences in Terrell County, Georgia. They discuss their childhood memories of Southwest Georgia, and how they came to meet and marry. The remainder of the interview focuses on their involvement in the Civil Rights Movement, the harassment they faced from white supremacists, and their role in registering black voters.
    - Moving Images, 1 video file (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (31 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0062_mv01
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (16 pages); afc2010039_crhp0062_Holloway_transcript
  - Sam Mahone oral history interview conducted by Hasan Kwame Jeffries in Albany, Georgia, March 9, 2013
    Biographical History: Sam Mahone was a civil rights activist with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) in Americus, Georgia. He attended Tougaloo College and the Art Institute of Atlanta and worked in several art museums and galleries.
    Summary: Sam Mahone discusses his experiences of racial segregation and discrimination in Americus, Georgia, and how he came to be involved in the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). After he joined SNCC, he participated in an array of activism: picketing a segregated movie theater, registering voters, and organizing in the black community. He also discusses the arrests that he and other activists experienced due to their activism, including the Americus Four case and the Leesburg Stockade. He concludes the interview by discussing his current involvement in showcasing African American art.
    - Moving Images, 1 video file (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (63 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0063_mv01
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (29 pages); afc2010039_crhp0063_Mahone_transcript
  - Robert McClary oral history interview conducted by Hasan Kwame Jeffries in Albany, Georgia, March 9, 2013
    Biographical History: Robert McClary was a civil rights activist with the Southwest Georgia Project in Worth County, Georgia.
    Summary: In this short interview, Robert McClary discusses his involvement in the Southwest Georgia Project. McClary describes attending mass meetings in Worth County, Georgia, and he discusses his work with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC). Along with keeping the books, he registered voters and informed people about welfare services.
    - Moving Images, 2 video files of 2 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (28 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0064_mv01-02
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (14 pages); afc2010039_crhp0064_McClary_transcript
  - Johnnie Ruth McCullar oral history interview conducted by Hasan Kwame Jeffries in Albany, Georgia, March 9, 2013
    Biographical History: Johnnie Ruth McCullar was a civil rights activist with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee in Terrell County, Georgia. She also worked as a certified nursing assistant and paraprofessional teacher.
    Summary: Johnnie Ruth Browner McCullar describes growing up in southwest Georgia, attending segregated schools in Sasser, Georgia, and her work in the Civil Rights Movement in the 1960s. She was a secretary of the Terrell County Movement and she also participated in sit-ins and helped to register voters. McCullar reflects on the legacy of the movement, noting the changes in social and political life that she has witnessed during her life, but also recognizing present-day challenges.
    - Moving Images, 2 video files of 2 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (62 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0065_mv01-02
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (36 pages); afc2010039_crhp0065_McCullar_transcript
  - Sam Young, Jr., oral history interview conducted by Will Griffin in Albany, Georgia, March 9, 2013
    Biographical History: Sam Young, Jr., worked as a civil rights activist with the Southwest Georgia Project and also as a printer and farmer.
    Summary: Samuel J. Young, Jr., describes his childhood in Worth County, Georgia, during the 1950s. He recalls the racial violence that he witnessed and heard stories about as a child. After graduating high school he joined the Southwest Georgia Project. He helped to start a newspaper for the project and was also involved in the group's initiative to develop a self-sufficient farm to counteract discrimination against black farmers.
    - Moving Images, 2 video files of 2 (Apple ProRes 422 HQ, QuickTime wrapper) (42 min.): digital, sound, color; afc2010039_crhp0066_mv01-02